When you look at the situation in the
Middle East today and
you you have a lot experience and you
know the region,
these officers, CIA officers that go to
the Middle East, do they have any sort
of
strategy? Do they know of the US
strategy in the Middle East or they're
they're giving them some sort of
missions, some sort of, you know, duties
to to
>> right?
>> What is that? Because after all, when
you are a a CIA officer or someone who's
working for CIA,
you you just see that as a duty or you
want to know a bigger picture of what's
going on because
>> that's a great question, Nema. That's
that's an important question. Um, first
of all, most of the officers that the
CIA sends to the Middle East um are not
Middle East experts and do not speak
Arabic.
>> Um, almost none of the CIA's officer
officers in the Middle East have a
longterm view. And it's because the
American government usually does not
have a long-term view. The CIA has
something called operating directives,
OD, and it goes from a level zero, which
means they're coming over the embassy
walls right now,
to level five, which means, you know, if
you happen to hear anything about, you
know, growing corn in Morocco,
just send us a a little message. So
tier zero level zero is the most
important that is like nuclear
proliferation
uh Iran
uh
the war in Russia and Ukraine that kind
of thing is tier zero tier one means
drop what you're doing and focus on this
and it's things like terrorism for
example
uh or threats to an American embassy And
then it goes down from there, tier 2,
three, four, to the point where it's
nobody really cares about the lower
tiers. But that's not to say that any of
these tiers are for a long-term view.
This was one of the things that I
enjoyed the most when I was serving in
the Middle East as an as an analyst.
It's because your job was to look at the
long-term view. I was interested in,
let's say, Saudi stability over the next
30 years. That's interesting to me.
What's not interesting is what's going
to happen in the next 24 hours in Sudan,
for example. I I I really don't care.
But a lot of CIA people do care. And so,
they're going to be focused on Sudan in
the next 24 hours or the next 48 hours
or what happens in the next round of
talks in Libya, as another example.
um or what's happening is Yemen going to
split back into two different Yemens.
Um and I think that that frankly it does
a disservice to the policy maker because
the policymaker for the most part can
get that information by reading the New
York Times or Al Jazzer or the
Washington Post. So the CIA is not
adding anything to the body of
intelligence. It should be focused on
the long term and it's not.
And whose decision is that for this sort
of policy?
>> Is that coming from the president and
his office?
>> Yeah, it it originates in the National
Security Council. So these are supposed
to be the issues that are the most um
important for the president and for
policy makers at that level, the
Secretary of State, the Secretary of
Defense, the the National Security
Adviser. And then those orders come down
to the CIA director. and from the C CIA
director to the um operational division
directors. So every year in December,
let's say I'm working for Neareastern
operations, the division director is
going to say, "Okay, everybody in the
near east division, this is what we're
going to collect on over the next year.
We're going to collect on Iran and the
nuclear program and Syria and what's
what China's doing in the Middle East,
things like that, things that that are
the most important. And then if you
happen to pick up something that is less
important but still interesting, write
it down, send it in, and we'll let the
analysts have it.
Then are they going to do they consider
the feedback they're getting from their
anal their officers in their for example
in the region you see what is their take
what is your understanding of what this
the situation there because after all
when you have someone on the ground
gathering information his view his sort
of understanding would be important is
that
>> you are so right you are so right and
the the obvious answer should yes, that
they're very focused on that.
Unfortunately, the true answer is no.
They don't care. And I'll give you an
example. This is a dated example. I I
was writing a paper. I was still on the
analytic side. I was writing a paper
um that touched on women's uh role in
politics in a Middle Eastern country.
And there was one woman in particular
that I was very interested in because
she she was out there in the media all
the time, fighting for the women's right
to vote and um and a real leader where
the international media were seeking her
out and getting her opinion and she was
very outspoken. She would come to the
United States and speak to women's
groups. So I sent a cable through uh
there's a uh a a tasking office at the
CIA. So I went to this tasking office
and I said, "I have these eight
questions about this woman. Could you
send the questions to the station and
have the station assign an officer to
find the information that I need?" So
they did and about 3 weeks later I got a
very short cable in response to my
questions and it said, "Oh yes, uh, this
woman is well known to us. We call her
the hot dog lady because we understand
that when she was living in the United
States, she loved hot dogs. And here in
the Middle East, it's hard to find hot
dogs. And so she has them shipped from
somewhere, Beirut or something. And she
likes them with mustard and relish and
this and that. And I'm like, "What the
[__] are you talking about? This I can't
send this to the president."
And so I went back to the tasking office
and I said, "This was a complete failure
to collect the information necessary to
send to the president. I can't tell the
president in response to his question,
should I take this woman seriously
because she wants to meet at the White
House?" I can't say, "Oh, well, I don't
know if you should take her seriously,
but she really loves hot dogs and this
is what she likes on her hot dogs."
That was when I learned that there was a
real split between the director of
operations and the director of
intelligence. And the director of
operations was going to do its thing.
And it didn't care what the director of
intelligence was writing and sending to
the president.
>> Yeah. John, one of the the reason I ask
you this question is the situation in
Ukraine because we know what's going on
in Ukraine in terms of the what is
happening to the military of Ukraine is
you know Russia is somehow
advancing underground but
how how do you see the role of the CIA
in gathering information from Ukraine on
the ground, the information that are
firthand information. I'm not talking
about they're getting it from, you know,
British or any other intelligence.
Are they really getting the information
directly from from Ukraine or they're
getting through these channels? It's
it's my understanding that there are CIA
officers, senior CIA officers stationed
inside the Ukrainian intelligence
service to provide support and liaison.
Uh and there are CIA officers on the
ground with Ukrainian um military or
special forces units. In addition, we
know that the CIA is training Ukrainian
uh military officers here in the United
States at bases in te Texas and I think
North Carolina. Uh so yeah, the the CIA
is getting the information directly from
the horse's mouth. But
uh but the Ukrainians are losing.
This war is untenable.
Every observer will tell you that the
Russians control the the line of
demarcation
and in the end CIA or no CIA, the
Ukrainians are going to have to come to
some kind of an agreement with the
Russians. This is one of those
situations, Nema, where the CIA is not
going to be able to to win this thing
for for the Ukrainians. This is going to
have to be between the Russians and the
Ukrainians. And sure, CIA help may have
may have delayed a Russian victory, may
have cost the Russians, you know, more
casualties,
but it can't go on forever.
>> Yeah.
John,
we know what has happened in 2014 in
Ukraine with the coup,
>> but do you see the same sort of policy
happening in the aftermath of any
Ukrainian settlement? Because
what Russia sees in Ukraine today is
they want a permanent solution to the
case of Ukraine and a security
architecture for the region.
You you cannot you know make obstacles
for CIA, MI6 or these intelligence. So
Russian intelligence as well. They're
doing their job. You know it's it's
common. It's you know it's normal to do
that. But when it comes to the
securities of these superpowers, you
have to have some sort of limitation to
the activities that you're, you know,
committed to.
Is that going to be considered? Do you
do you see that sort of will in the
Trump administration to consider that?
>> I think so. I agree with you. Whatever
solution
the two sides come to, in the end, it
has to be a permanent solution. And I
think we've seen the indications of what
that solution is going to be. It's going
to have to be that the Russians keep
Donetsk, Luhansk, uh, Kerone, Crimea.
The Russian speaking areas that they
control de facto now, I think they'll
end up controlling uh, uh, formally
once this is over.
I think that another Russian red line is
that Ukraine cannot ever be a member of
NATO. But that's a misnomer, Nema,
because Ukraine doesn't have to be a
member of NATO. Uh Australia is not a
member of NATO. Japan, South Korea,
Saudi Arabia, UAE, they're not members
of NATO. They're what's called major
non-NATO allies. That's an official
status. And I wouldn't be surprised if
the United States agrees with the
Russians that no, Ukraine should not be
a member of NATO. It will never be a
member of NATO, but it could be granted
major non-NATO ally status, thus giving
it essentially the same rights as a NATO
country. And I think what the Russians
will concede is that Ukraine will get
fasttrack um uh membership in the
European Union. And then the EU begins
the rebuilding of Ukraine
>> and that's going to be the end of it.
But I I really do believe that
we're nearing the end and the end is not
going to be what the United States and
Ukraine have hoped for, but it's going
to be enough to put this thing to to
rest.
>> Yeah. Many people believe,
at least in our audience, that CIA is
part of deep state.
CIA is, you know,
do you think that the leadership usually
in CIA is part of the establishment or
the the establishment has a lot of
leverage on CIA in the way that they're
using CIA?
>> No, I I I agree that there is a deep
state and the CIA's an important
probably the most important part of the
deep state. But let's let's define what
a deep state is. In my view, a deep
state is a group of unelected,
very powerful bureaucrats
that can do what the president wants or
they can ignore what the president wants
because presidents come and go every
four years or every eight years. And
these deep state leaders are in their
positions for 20, 30, even 35 years.
Presidents come and go and these deep
sters remain. And so if there's a policy
that a president supports or wants and
it's a policy that the deep state
leadership does not like, they just wait
until the president's not president
anymore.